If you want to write something that's going to
affect people emotionally, you have to do it emotionally.
And it has to cost you
more than the time you're spending writing.
It pushes me to my emotional and intellectual capabilities.
I feel like when something is working, it is because all cylinders are firing
and I am working at the very bleeding edge of what I am capable of.
Storytelling is a huge part of the human experience.
But how do you tell a good story?
There's the cliché of a writer sitting at a desk
wrestling with the page, trying to find their ever-evasive muse.
There are elements of craft to consider, for sure.
But for many authors, creativity comes from a place deep
within themselves, and it looks different from writer to writer.
So, what's the secret behind an unforgettable story?
Welcome to Harvard Thinking, a podcast where
the life of a writer is a mystery.
Where the life of the mind meets everyday life.
Today, I'm joined by…
James Wood. I'm a professor of the practice
of literary criticism at Harvard in the English department.
He's also a literary critic for The New Yorker and
the author of multiple books, including How Fiction Works. Then…
Sam Marks. I am a senior lecturer in the English
department in playwriting, and I also teach a TV writing class.
For the past three years, he was
also the director of creative writing. Then…
Lauren Groff. I'm a novelist and writer.
I'm a short story writer, and
I own a bookstore in Gainesville, Florida.
She was a 2018-2019 Radcliffe Fellow, and three of
her novels have been finalists for the National Book Award.
And our final guest…
Nick White. I'm a short story writer and a novelist.
He's also an associate senior
lecturer on fiction at Harvard.
And I'm Samantha Liney-Perfoss, your host
and a writer for the Harvard Gazette.
Today, we'll talk about storytelling with four writers, and
how they take an idea and bring it to life.
What is it that gets a story started for you?
Is it an image or a character? Where do you begin?
It depends on the situation
and the story that's being told.
So, sometimes it'll be something that I've
been thinking about for a very long time.
It doesn't become a story until I experience something or
I read something else that collides with the initial idea,
that sort of blooms into a story
with urgency and density and gravity and weight.
And after that happens, it takes a
much longer time to build in the subconscious.
To me, I often am thinking about a thing, an idea or
a character or a moment or an experience, like, for a long time.
But I think that the story itself
doesn't actually happen until I start writing it.
That's when it actually unfolds.
I found that generally, like, writing is not successful for
me if I'm like, oh, and then this crazy twist happens.
Like, that's usually a disaster.
And so it's a combination of something I've been thinking about for
a long time and also the immediate thread of whatever is going.
It's in some ways like I'm not a musician, but like a
musician improvising, like you're searching for the right note or lick or whatever.
And then you find the harmony and
you kind of take it where it goes.
I apologize to all the musicians out there who
are like, this guy doesn't know what he's talking about.
Yeah, I think I do a mix of both.
There are still stories that I want to write that I think I've been thinking
about for years that I just haven't figured out yet how to bring to the page.
And then there are stories
that come more easily to me.
And then once I have what Anne Lamont calls that shitty first draft, I
have something I can work with and shape once it's outside of my head.
Because I think all my stories sound
good to me when they're inside my head.
And then when I put them in the cold, harsh light of the page
and begin to go back and inspect it, I can see all its weaknesses.
But then I have something
tangible that I can work with.
I think speaking in terms of like images or characters, oftentimes for me, I find writing begins with a particular character
and then just figuring out what that character wants and what is getting in the way of what that character wants.
I like this question because if I think of beginnings, literally for me, knowing what a
first line might be or knowing what an ending might be is very helpful to me.
I have much less experience than
the other panelists in actually writing stories.
For instance, I've never written
a short story in my life.
I don't think I could.
But if I expand slightly the definition of a narrative to be, say, a nonfiction account or even stretching it a little bit here, even a review, it can
be very helpful to me sometimes, even if I don't know what's going to go in the middle of something, to know where I'm beginning and where I'm ending.
Just knowing where I'm ending can do it.
Nick, you mentioned characters.
There's this idea out there about how you might think of a character, but then once they exist, they take on a
life of their own and they start to do things that you maybe didn't think they were going to do when you started.
Do any of you find that to be true?
Or in what ways do you wrestle
with the character development within your stories?
I love when that happens.
I'm working on a novel right now.
I have like things in the draft broadly outlined.
But the sort of scenes that I begin to write sometimes, especially when I have two or more characters
in a scene, it can sometimes, especially in those first drafts, feel a little bit like a science experiment.
So seeing how these characters are going to spark off of each other or putting the character in a
particular situation, it can be really exciting to sort of go with it and have a kind of like looseness.
I'm currently reading that book, Tony at Random,
which is about Toni Morrison being an editor.
And there's somewhere in the book
where they talk about how she,
thinks about characters when she's writing as whispering over
her ear and telling her like, oh, that's just right.
That's right.
Oh, nope.
That's not good enough.
I wish I could experience characters like that.
I think that's a beautiful way of thinking about it.
Yeah.
A lot of times when I write
plays, like the characters, I don't see them.
I hear them.
It's an oral, a U R A L form.
And I often feel like they've come or they've appeared in my head or my imagination
or whatever the play for a reason, but I didn't might not know what it is.
And so it's, let's see.
I think it's a good way to
think about where we all go together.
I think it also varies.
Like sometimes characters are incredibly strong and they're very
clear and you have a really good sense of them.
And then sometimes they're more hazy and you have to spend more time
with them and like chip away or see how they reveal themselves to you.
I think often we think of character as a fixed idea
that we have of specific people, but everyone is an animal.
And so I think character can
shift radically depending on the environment.
And so I think character can have
the same people having a breakup scene.
But if you have it on a beach versus on
the top of Mount Everest, it's going to go very differently.
So paying attention to not only whatever that is the inflexible center of what your conception of this person is, but
also paying attention to the true animal nature of being a person in the world is really important at the same time.
Lauren, there was an interview that you did.
And you were describing your
creative process as a nuclear fusion.
I was wondering if you could talk a little bit
more about that and what exactly that means for you.
Yeah, it's really like my
literature is born out of literature.
And I think it's possible to write
a novel without ever having read a novel.
But I think it's very vanishingly rare and
it probably would be a very bad book.
Just my opinion.
James can tell us whether or not that's true.
But I think if you have speak yourself
in literature, in ideas, in other people's voices.
And you're listening to the ghost of George Eliot
and Charles Dickens and Toni Morrison and Langston Hughes.
You're going through your day listening to these things.
Of course, it's going to be nuclear, right?
Because your ideas are always going to explode
when they come in contact with other people.
So I think that is one of the great and moving
joys and mysteries and beauties of living this life of writing.
You are constantly surrounded by
explosive ideas of other people.
Can I just go back to the character thing?
Aristotle basically wrote the Poetics, which is like a doctrine
on how to write plays in a very specific way.
But they're very influential.
Puts characters subservient to action, right?
So that anything that the character does that
doesn't feed the action to him is extraneous.
I don't think that we live in that model anymore.
But there's a sort of spectrum I think of as
like character driven versus plot driven and how that goes.
And I think sometimes it seems dishonest if
a character is shoehorned into the plot, right?
But then also sometimes there's the experience of
listening to characters where you're like, I don't care.
What's the story?
So I think it's like
a, I think it's a balance.
But Sam, the thing about
the action and character breaking apart.
Actually, if you think of a great deal of the
kind of TV writing that I'm sure you would never do,
but that is just the stuff that's out there
now, an enormous amount of it is just simply,
plotting for the sake of plotting.
Yeah.
With ridiculous twists and turns that even within the confines
of the thriller genre don't really make any sense at all.
And you'll sometimes encounter a piece by a student
and it'll be trundling along and then suddenly in effect,
they get into a spaceship and go off to Mars and
you say, now, why did you do that thing on page eight?
And they'll just say, I don't know.
I just, because I can, I just felt like it.
So this is a bit of a problem.
I fully agree with that.
I think that so many students and so many writers in general, like
sometimes I think about writing as a process of confronting how you confront challenge.
And I think often it's like, I want to quit.
I want to take a break.
I want to have a drink or whatever.
I want to have a spaceship, right?
I want someone to rescue me from the process of having to figure out
what the heck I have to do because to figure it out is incredibly painstaking.
Right.
And that's the like cliche of the writer, like tearing their hair
out or whatever, because it is hard to figure out what happens next.
I'm now thinking of this story that ends with a character going
off in a spaceship and what my response to the student would be.
The story begins when they
enter the spaceship and go off.
Why are they, that's the beginning.
I also liked what you said about a lot of times how we deal with conflict
in our everyday lives is like related to how we do that in our writerly sense.
I can feel that, but I also feel that there are ways in which I
allow my characters to be much braver on the page than I am and much bolder.
And I think that is a really great
way to think about fiction and inhabiting characters.
Have your characters do the
thing that you're afraid to do.
I think that is a really interesting prompt.
That actually makes me think like we've talked
about character driven, we've talked about plot driven.
I'm also curious how much of it
is like soul of the writer driven.
How much of yourselves do you feel
like you are putting into these stories?
I think for me, my
first novel was very much author-driven.
It wasn't very much autobiographical, but it was
also kind of like an alternative history for myself.
It dealt a lot with conversion therapy and being gay
from Mississippi and having a family that would not be accepting.
And dealing with all of that mess and trauma on the page
in a way that I felt unable to do in my real life.
But I also have been thinking a lot about this because
I've been talking to my students a lot about setting and place.
And I find it really ironic that I spent
so much of my time growing up in Mississippi.
I'm from a really small town called Possum Neck.
And I spent my whole life
waiting to leave, couldn't wait to leave.
And as soon as I leave the state, I
immediately start trying to write my way back in.
I do feel that tension a lot in my work.
And I still set things in Mississippi
and I go back and visit a lot.
And that place has been very fruitful for me.
And I'm grateful for whatever
the river of my imagination is.
I once had a writing teacher, Carol
Maso, who's a fiction writer, who said,
You can't make anyone a better writer. You
can only help them get closer to their obsessions.
And I feel like the more I write, not all
of my plays are set in Harvard or New York.
But even if I try to write something differently,
I inevitably write about a version of the same thing.
Which I don't think is bad. In some ways,
I feel like I've succeeded on some of them.
Not to say that you repeat yourself, but
that you're working out some of the same questions.
Right.
Questions of the self, even if
they take place in different settings.
I also think it's interesting
that you keep writing about Mississippi.
I think it's like, we know these places
are in our souls or our bones or whatever.
And I think that those are
assets as a writer, not bad things.
I think you're writing from the deepest part of yourself.
Even if you're writing something that is set on a
spaceship, something that is so far from your lived experience,
it's still autobiographical in a very real way, even if the
contours of the story don't accord to the contours of your life.
Because it's so deeply personal.
Every character is a prismatic hologram of who you are.
I love to play with the titration
of closeness that I'm giving the reader.
That this is a joyous thing to play with.
The trick of writing something that is beyond your
autobiographical details, but is still, it really feels deeply personal.
That is a lot of very hard work for me.
And it takes me a really
long time to work myself into it.
And I do it through the music of the line.
I can only do it by
playing and failing vastly, so often.
And then finally finding a piece of music that
corresponds to this story that I'm trying to tell.
But I think all of it is
the soul if you're doing it right.
Lauren, I have a question for you.
As you've been writing in historical
periods, remote-ish from the contemporary recently,
and whether you'd had the experience
of recognizing an autobiographical motif or impulse,
even if it seemed to be
in a completely different fictional universe.
Yeah, Marie de France et moi.
I mean, every grandiose idea she had is my idea.
That's me right there.
And the girl in the Bastard Wilds, that's me.
As a panicked young person alone, which
I've been many times in the woods running.
Like I've done that.
Sometimes I access that, even if the people are distant
from me in temporal terms or in even demographic terms.
Like you find it through the body.
You find it through the sensory
information that you're getting from the world.
I wrote a book about
a 1960s utopian commune called Arcadia.
I've never lived in a commune, but I have in
fact actually held a handmade blue bowl filled with warm oatmeal.
I know how that feels.
And so that is me right there holding
that when it's actually the character holding that, right?
So you find the bodily information that allows
you to access the rest of the world.
Lauren, you mentioned failure.
What does failure look like?
It's so funny that we're doing this for the Harvard
community because I think most people have never failed ever.
And I love failure.
I actually, like, I go after it.
I have OCD.
And so it's actually really hard for me
to do something and let it be imperfect.
I have developed a process which is insane, but it allows me to embrace failure in the
way that a child would embrace failure if they're trying to build like a Lego castle, right?
If it doesn't work, they just
trash it and start over again.
And it's just joyous.
You're just playing.
You're just figuring things out.
It's delightful.
So I'm purely analog, right?
I only write with my pen.
I don't write on a
computer until the very, very end.
I don't even read my drafts ever.
I write a full draft and
then I put it to the side.
I start over again as many times
as necessary because I'm actually embracing failure.
I actually want to know the limits
of my ability to tell this story.
And then it starts to grow
its own ability to tell itself eventually.
If you do it enough
times, then it's not me, right?
I'm not the one writing it.
I'm the book itself that has come up against all of these
obstacles and is teaching me how to put it down on the page.
Failure in our society has so
many negative, so much negative baggage.
But if you're thinking about it as pure play the whole way through until the story itself
starts to talk to you and tell you what you need to do, then that's just pure joy.
That's like sheer pleasure.
And so I really love the failed draft.
I love the first shitty thing.
I don't want anyone to ever read
because they couldn't because my handwriting is egregious.
I let it all in.
I let the failure in because
it's how you understand the world.
That's an amazing thing.
Were you saying, Lauren, if you're 100 pages into a manuscript or even just
20 pages into a manuscript, you don't sit down and read that 20 pages.
You just keep going.
Oh, just a quick note for our listeners.
Lauren is now holding up a notebook.
This is what I'm working on now.
And I'll never read it over again.
It just doesn't it doesn't matter.
Wow.
That's amazing.
Fascinating to us.
The other two, Nick and
Sam, do you work like that?
I have yellow legal notepads that I write on when I'm
like trying to just figure out the bones of the story.
And then I'll go to the computer and I'll type up
what I imagine is going to be like the first chapter.
And then I'll print that out and set it aside.
And look at it again.
And then I'll make corrections on that.
And then I'll open up another Word document.
And I'll go back to the yellow legal pad.
So I do like a mix of that.
But I also find that when I'm working on a
project, I carry it around with me everywhere I go.
For me, writing is the
stuff I do at my desk.
Yes.
But it's also the stuff
I'm thinking about when I'm walking.
My partner likes to say
that I live in the clouds.
And I think that is
like something that I struggle with.
It's like being present a lot of the
time because I am thinking about the story.
And the kind of ways in
which I've written myself into a corner.
Or things that I don't quite yet
understand about a character or a situation.
And it feels a lot like there's
these little knots that I'm slowly untying.
I think for me, time is a great teacher.
When I'm drafting in the like heat of the
draft, I can convince myself what I've written is brilliant.
Then I go back the next day.
And I look at it with perhaps more sober eyes.
And I'm like, oh, this is not actually brilliant.
I think that shitty first draft thing is accurate.
It's like a weird altered state.
Where it's like I'm writing and I don't really know.
Like when I go back
and I'm like, I wrote that?
Oh, that's cool.
Like literally, like I've forgotten what I've written.
And then for me, I
do that a couple of drafts.
And then once you find what it is, then
there's like a more of the craft comes in.
Then I have to be like
a different kind of writer for myself.
What am I trying to do in this scene?
What is it really about?
And then molding it.
But that first phase of just going
is the hardest and most exciting thing.
James, you mentioned about beginnings and
trying to find the first sentence.
And I was thinking a lot about that.
And I often think that revision for me in the drafting process is
a way of pulling it out of myself and where I'm the only reader.
But start thinking about there's going
to be other readers to this.
And start thinking about like a reader.
And one of the things that a writing teacher once told me about
beginnings that I think is so important is that when you begin a story,
you also through discourse begin to teach
the reader how to read the story.
And I feel like the process of revision is like
thinking about that reader constantly and who that reader is.
I love that.
I was just so interested to hear from all
of you because most of my writing is professionalized reviewing.
This is like 4,000 words, 5,000 words at the most.
And so it's completely different.
And I tend to begin at
the beginning and end at the end.
And that means I obsessively
have to get the beginning right.
The first couple of paragraphs
have to be the right ones.
And once I've got that, then everything
can flow and it flows fairly quickly.
But that first bit can be extremely slow.
Can I ask a question about your process, James?
Let's say you're reading a novel.
Yeah.
What's the process of reading and synthesizing your
experience to writing what you thought about it?
So the first reading, like most of us, I'm sure I read with
a pen in hand and I'm putting lines under things and dog-earing pages.
But I try to just suspend judgment as much as
possible and let the experience of the book have its way.
And then when I go back to the things
that I thought were interesting, why did I dog-ear that?
Oh, there's that passage. I really liked
that image or whatever it was, that word.
And then when I'm doing that,
I think I'm assembling some kind of argument.
But I think that first reading, I
try to be fairly open and innocent.
That's how I tell my students to read each
other's work in workshops, is read it at least twice.
The first read is what I
call the honeymoon read, where anything goes.
This is just like a fun read. Let
the piece just have its way with you.
So what's after the honeymoon read?
Well, then it's the seven-year itch.
Where is it?
It's the seven-year itch. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's when you get the pen out and
you start, like, that thing that you first read.
And then you're like, oh, I just adored. You're like, dear God, does
he have to use a conjunctive adverb every time he makes a contrasting point?
James, I also, I was just thinking
about what actually makes a good story?
And is it possible to be objectively good?
Or does the reader just bring so
much of their own selves to a text?
I know I have picked up titles
that were raved about by critics or friends.
And I get two chapters in and
I'm like, it's just not for me.
So as a professional critic, I'm
wondering your take on that question.
I would say, and I bet I'm joined here by everyone else, that I'm responding to and looking
for a kind of vitality, a sort of just a sort of liveliness and life on the page.
And in that sense, once you've got that,
other questions like, is this a realist novel?
Is this a postmodern experimental novel?
Is it broken into numbered paragraphs?
All that stuff.
That's not to the point, is it?
The thing that we're trying to feel and find
is just something very alive that draws you in.
I have a very strong memory of back in about 2011, standing in
the kitchen at the kitchen counter and opening a package from Archipelago Books.
And they had sent me just on
spec the first volume of the book.
And that's a cover of Canaris Guards, My Struggle.
And I didn't know anything about it.
I'd never heard of him.
I knew nothing about it.
And it was just like a little note saying,
this seems like you might be interested in this.
So I opened it and I just started reading it.
And I was standing there for three or four pages.
And I thought, this has something, this has it.
It's drawing me in, it has real vitality.
So above all, I'm just looking
for that thing, the non deadness.
When I pick up a book
to read it, I am always,
Always, I think, in the mindset where
I am reading with my arms uncrossed.
Like, I want to be impressed.
I want to be taken somewhere.
I want to sort of be drawn in.
And I never underestimate a book or a
story's power to just make me forget everything else.
Thinking about that vitality or that life, I feel like that might be
a sign that a story is working, either for you or just in general.
As you are writing your own stories, how
do you know whether or not it's working?
If it comes close, you can feel it.
It's almost like a vibrational thing.
You're writing into it.
It feels good, right?
Even if it feels bad to write it, it feels good because you're coming
as close as possible to this thing that you want so badly to do.
And that doesn't mean that everyone who's going to read it is
going to like it, right, or going to feel the same vibration.
But you feel it.
And you sense it.
And you know that it's there.
And it takes a very long time as a writer
to actually develop a sense of that in your own work.
I just really appreciate, Lauren, how much you talk about how
things feel at the vibrations and the physical nature of it.
I feel like you're talking about success at Harvard.
And I think that a thing at Harvard,
you're right, most of the students are very successful.
And most of the success has come at an intellectual level
as they plan their plays or their things in some ways.
But I think just returning to feeling
or vibrations, I just find it really useful.
And I think I've learned a lot.
I think I might use it in my class.
That's all.
And I'll credit you.
I'll credit you.
Good.
Sometimes we do have to detach our intellect from the thing
that we're trying to do because it's not all about intellect.
Eventually, in the editing process, that's when we apply it.
If you want to write something that's going to
affect people emotionally, you have to do it emotionally.
And it has to cost you
more than the time you're spending writing.
It pushes me to my emotional and intellectual capabilities.
I feel like when something is working,
it is because all cylinders are firing.
And I am working at the very
bleeding edge of what I am capable of.
I'd also say, just as a tip, I don't
know if it's useful for any of our listeners.
First of all, I tend to just quietly read under
my breath as I'm reading through a paragraph or two.
I just, I quietly read it
so that I can get a sense.
But I also think, actually, just a more vocal
version of that, of actually reading something out aloud.
It's interesting, isn't it?
When you read from your work in a
bookshop, I don't know if others have had this.
I've certainly had it.
You agree to read a few pages, and
suddenly you find you've edited out a sentence.
It's like some weird kind of bullshit detector went off, and
you thought, ah, I can't pull that one off on the room.
And there's probably a good reason for that, right?
And it should have been
left out in the original book.
So I just think that's the estranging thing.
Always it's a kind of, you want estrangement, don't you?
Because you're trying to split yourself into two.
This other person, this colder.
This person who is ready to murder
the darlings will ideally read what you've written.
And that's very difficult to do.
Reading aloud is so important.
I work in my office here at Lamont, and I'm sure that when I was back at OSU as
a professor there, my colleagues who were nearby probably thought I was insane because I'm reading my stuff aloud.
And it must appear that I am, in some ways, having a
breakdown, especially depending on what part of the story or chapter I'm reading.
But that is so true.
James, you mentioned the phrase, murder your darlings.
Mm-hmm.
Just in case there's people listening who are
not familiar with that because it sounds pretty morbid.
But it's this idea that you may have these beloved passages or sentences or
characters even, but you have to kill them for the greater good of the story.
Does it get easier to murder your darlings?
I think it does.
I certainly have memories of being much younger and reacting badly to editors,
possessively and somewhat neurotically, and storming around the house for a couple of days.
And then I think just having enough of those experiences,
you begin to realize that there is wisdom outside oneself.
Editors have saved my ass so many times.
I remember in a story for my story collection, my editor,
Kate Napolitano, if you ever hear this, she was so brilliant.
She had a great bullshit detector.
I remember there was one line in one
of my stories where I said, he wept.
And she put a little note
there that said, who is he, Jesus?
And I just cut it out.
And I was like, oh, I don't know.
Like, I think I like this,
but she's saying cut it out.
And I cut it out.
And then I go back and revisit the story.
Like, it just works so much better.
Like, everything she's ever told me to
cut out, I have done and followed.
And it made it so much better.
I totally agree that murdering all
of that gets so much easier.
It becomes a sociopath almost for your bad lines.
I have a little counter to this.
Gentle pushback.
Obviously, yes, kill your darlings.
Yes, of course, edit.
And it does get easier.
I think that's true.
That said, sometimes things are difficult and people don't
like them, but it doesn't mean you should cut them.
I'm not saying you need to be willfully difficult, but like that
you do things that even though they may not be immediately appealing.
Right.
It goes back to the TV conversation.
So much TV is bad because it's like always rewarding.
And there's a place for that.
But there's also a place
for things that don't reward immediately.
I'm just saying that in the killing
of your darlings discussion, you have to balance.
Do I need this?
Is this bad?
Who is this telling?
And that's why it makes it hard.
Right.
Maybe I haven't done a good enough job
of writing the thing I want to write.
It's not that I should cut it.
It's that I should write it better.
That's the challenge.
That's what good editing is.
It's sort of sliding those moments where there's
no life or there's less life than you need.
It's not telling you to cut something.
It's telling you it needs to be better.
Everyone needs an editor.
One of my greatest writing teachers, Michelle Herman, she had this famous mark that she would put on your stories and
they were brackets and she would bracket a sentence and she would just write out on the side, do better here.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
And it really worked.
I'm having flashbacks to my early writing career and how a comment
like that would have caused me to just have a total breakdown.
And I would take it so personally.
But I do think with experience and perspective,
you realize that there's nothing to take personally.
We all benefit from having
other people weigh in on stuff.
We all make bad art on
the way to making good art.
And I think like, it's just the way it is.
As we wrap up this episode,
do you have any advice for others?
For other writers out there?
One of the things I found has been very useful in
talking to my students, especially when we're working on short stories.
But more than ever, when we're working on novels
is thinking about your process and thinking about your schedule.
I'm teaching a novel workshop next semester.
And one of the first things that we're going to do is talk
about our schedule, making time for the practice of writing in our daily lives.
And I think that has always been something
that has saved me, even when I'm feeling stuck.
I know that every Monday from seven in the morning to 10,
I'm going to spend three hours that Monday thinking about my work.
Even if I don't put a mark
on the page, I'm still thinking about it.
I'm still wrestling with it.
I think Peter Ho Davies, who teaches at University of Michigan, talks about you don't
have to write every day, but you still need to touch your work every day.
And I think that is something that has always helped me when I feel
like I'm failing and I don't know my way out of a particular story.
My instinct, going back to what Sam said about like how we deal with conflict, is to run away,
is to procrastinate, is to not, it's just watch a really bad television show or do something that's not writing.
But that's the time when I need to
go to the work and sit with it.
Writing is more a verb than it is a noun.
It's the process.
What you're doing is like focused on the process.
That's the art.
And if you happen to have something at the end
of it that other people don't have, that's the art.
That's the art that other people can read.
That's great.
That allows you to do it again.
I don't know if anybody ever gave
this advice, but it feels like someone did.
So I'm just going to go with it.
There really are no rules, right?
If you look at the great works of literature, Tolstoy
does everything that he wants to do because he can, right?
So it's really only the rules inherent to
the story at hand that you need to discover.
And then everything else you
just figure out as you're going.
So do not be hidebound, do
not be rule-bound, do not be afraid.
Go courageously into the work
and the work will reward you.
Lovely.
I love that.
Thank you all for joining me today.
Thanks, Sam.
Thank you.
Thanks for listening.
To see a transcript of this episode or to
listen to our other episodes, visit harvard.edu slash thinking.
If you're a fan of this podcast and want to
support our work, share it with a friend or colleague.
This episode was hosted and produced by me, Samantha
Liney-Parfos, with additional production and editing support from Sarah LaMotti.
Editing by Ryan Mulcahy, Paul Mikushima, and Max Larkin.
Original music and sound design by Noel Flatt.
Produced by Harvard University.
Copyright 2025.